玄黄端现 太极混沌如鸡蛋 随着
In the Beginning there was the darkness and then
轰的一声
BANG!
诞生了无限膨胀的时间 空间和物质
Giving birth to endless expanding existence of time, space and matter.
现在所见超乎我们的想象
Now we see further than we've ever imagined
超越了客观认知极限
beyond the limits of our existence
那地方我们称之为"宇宙"
in the place we call:The Universe.
太阳是银河系亿万恒星中的一颗
Our Sun is one of billions of stars in the Milky Way galaxy.
我们的星系是已知宇宙中千亿
And our galaxy is one of hundreds of billions,
可能万亿星系中的一个
maybe trillions in the now-known universe.
用哈勃望远镜 我们观察到的宇宙
From the Hubble space telescope comes a view of the universe that was
是穿越历史迷雾的壮丽旅行
a magnificent trip through the mists of history.
几乎回到宇宙大爆炸的时代
and back, nearly all the way to the Big Bang.
每一个点儿 每一个块儿
Each smudge, each clump,
每一个光子
each blob of light.
这边繁星成千上万
A billions stars here,
那边繁星成万上千
a trillions stars there.
如果你想知道我们在宇宙中的位置
If you want to know ours place in the Universe
来向上看
take a look up
在那遥远 遥远的地方
at far, far away.
去看那其它星系的疆界
to the realm of alien galaxies.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
历史频道·宇宙第一季第9集 外族星系
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：射手网 调校：TIAN@CMCT 招募Q号: 76846146
我们的宇宙是运动的宇宙
Ours is a universe of motion,
膨胀的宇宙
expansion,
光芒的宇宙
light,
还是昏暗的宇宙
and blackness.
我们的宇宙有136亿年的历史
We think the Universe is about 13.6 billion years old.
把它放着作一参照 地球
So just to put that in context, the Earth
和太阳系有40亿年的历史
and Solar System is just over 4 billion years old.
所以宇宙比地球的年龄大三倍
So the Universe is just over 3 times older than the Earth.
在广裹无垠的虚幻的边际
Across the vast reaches of the interstellar void,
遥远的星辰彼此之间
distant stars are held together by the long reach
受到引力的牵连
of the gravity's unyielding grip.
这些星辰经过了上百万年
Over billions of years these stars have come together
一起形成了星系
to form galaxies.
一个星系有数千亿的星辰
A galaxy is a collection of a hundred billions or so stars.
那些星辰相互既不接近 也不接触
And these stars are by no means touching each other or actually anywhere near each other.
和它们的体积相比 它们离的很远
Compare their sizes they are very, very far apart from the other.
想不通星系这东西怎么了
The thing that blows my mind about galaxies is what monsters they are.
它们大到不可想象
They are incredibly huge.
如果把太阳比作是一个句号
If the Sun was the size of a period on the page,
就象i 上的那一点
the dot of an i,
我们的星系将是整个美国大陆
our galaxy would be the size continental United States.
所以它们非常浩瀚
So, they are gigantic.
天文学家都知道有特殊的
Astronomers have always known there was something special
一群星辰和太空尘
about the band of stars and dust.
在他们上面环绕着夜空
that seemed encircle night sky above them.
这是我们的星系 一条白色的痕迹叫做
It is our galaxy, a white smutch they called:
银河系
The Milky Way.
那是一个光点的群体 光点
That band of light is the collective light
来自成千上万颗星
of hundreds of thousands of stars,
你用眼分不开它们 是希腊人命名的
which you cannot see it individually with your eye and that was named by the Greeks.
他们认为 看起来像是乳白色的河流
They thought look like milky river so they called the Milky Way.
我们的银河有数千亿的行星
There are a hundred billions stars in our galaxy,
宇宙里有数千亿个星系
and are a hundred billions galaxies in the observable Universe.
在宇宙里行星的数量多于
That's more stars in the Universe
地球海滩上的沙粒数
than grains of sand on the beaches of Earth.
如果想象星系同曲棍球一样大
If you imagine the galaxy itself is the size of a hockey puck,
那么星系彼此之间
then the galaxies are spaced from one to other
有几十公分的距离
about few diameters apart.
这儿有一个球 那儿有一个球
So there is a puck here, a puck over there,
星系在宇宙就象这样
that's kind way the galaxies are spaced in universe.
从哈勃望远镜得到的图片
Pictures from the Hubble space telescope
展示其它星系的多样性
show the wide variety of alien galaxies.
草帽星系
The Sombrero galaxy,
也叫M104
also known as M104.
巨大的星系团里最庞大的物体之一
One of the most massive objects in a gigantic cluster of galaxies,
草帽星系包含八千亿倍
the Sombrero galaxy contains nearly 800 billion times
我们的太阳的质量
as much mass as our Sun.
和银河系相比
Compared to the Milky Way,
草帽星系的肚子比它的盘子大得多
Sombrero has much large bulge relative to its highly coiled disc
它的图片就是典型的例子
This image of the Sombrero galaxy it is also a prime example
猜猜看会怎样 三个世界级的
what's happens when three of the worlds
天文望远镜联合起来
top telescopes joined forces.
查德拉X光观察台
The Chandra X-ray observatory,
把草帽星系发出来的
taking an image of high power X-rays
高能量的X光线成像
emitted by the Sombrero galaxy.
哈勃天文望远镜
The Hubble space telescope,
捕捉行走数百万光年的的
snapping an optical picture capturing the visual light,
可见光成像
that made multimillion light year journey to the Earth.
史匹哲天文望远镜
And the Spitzer space telescope,
利用红外线成像
capture an infrared vision,
得到草帽星系的热指纹
looking at Sombrero galaxy's heat signature.
三个图片结合起来 出现一个难忘的奇异景象
Melded together this 3 images provide a staggering  and unforgettable look
远离两千八百万光年的星系
at a galaxy 28 million light years away.
M51 涡状星系
M51, the Whirlpool galaxy.
它的旋臂如棉花糖般螺旋在一起
Its spiral arms twisting like cotton candy being spun.
星系的中央聚集着恒星
The center of the Whirlpool galaxy is so densely pack with stars,
谁有是住在那儿
anyone living on planets there,
将享受长白天
would be under a constant bright sky
无论是白天还是黑夜
day or night.
人马座A
Centaurus A
一个发射出大量电波的星系
a galaxy sending out  massive amounts of radio waves.
就像是星际的广播站
think it as a interstellar broadcaster
向宇宙日夜不停地发射信号
beaming its signal throughout the Universe all day, every day.
它是最近的活跃星系
It's the closest of the so called active galaxies.
从核心倾泻大量能量的星系
Galaxies that pour out tremendous amounts of energy from their cores.
这是一幅哈勃超深空图片
This is a Hubble ultra deep field image,
由哈勃天文望远镜拍摄
created using the Hubble space telescope,
它展示了广裹无垠的宇宙
it shows us how truly vast and distant the Universe really is.
远方的宇宙不只是空旷
And how those far spaces are anything but empty.
当你看宇宙的非常深处时 你看到的是以前的
When you look very deeply in the Universe, you're looking back in the time.
所以看到的星系都是很久很久以前的
So you're looking back galaxies, right back when they were very very young
只有现在年代几个百分点时的景象
when they're only few percent of their current age.
哈勃超深空图片就像是时间隧道
So the Hubble ultra deep field is like the time tunnel
给了我们一个地球诞生前星系的景象
gives us a glimpse of galaxies as they were before the Earth was in existence.
地球有四十亿年的历史
The Earth is 4 billion years old,
我们认为星系有一百三十亿年的历史
we think galaxies as they were 13 billion years old.
光线离开那些天体时
So the light left these objects
我们的星球还不存在
before there was any earth at all.
靠近我们的大星系 仙女座星系
The nearest large galaxy to us, the Andromeda galaxy
有两百万光年远
it's about 2 million light years away.
从仙女座星系来的光
So the light from the Andromeda galaxy,
要用两百万年才到这儿
takes 2 million years to get here.
所以 我们看到的是两百万年前的样子
so we're seeing it as it looked, 2 million years ago.
这是最近的星系
And that is one our nearby galaxies.
我们看更遥远的空间
As we look farther, farther out the space
我们会看到更遥远的过去
we will look farther, and farther back in time.
为了更好的理解
To get better idea of the concept,
去参观地球最为壮观的景色之一
just visit one of the most spectacular vistas on Earth,
雄伟的大峡谷
the Majestic Great Canyon
当观察较低的层时会看到久远的岩石
As you look down the layers you get older and older rocks
我们能辫别不同的环境
and we can tell what the different environments were.
我们可以准确了解这儿的地质史
so we can actually look at the geologic history of this area over time and in essence look back
通过这儿的环境了解数亿年前的地球史
through the environment that was located right here back over hundreds of millions of years in the Earth's history.
观察距离地球很远很远的星辰
So, by look at stars further and further away from the Earth
天文学家可以找到宇宙进化的线索
the astronomers can get an idea of the evolution of the Universe.
从早期的星系天文学始
From the earliest days of galactic astronomy
观察者就已经注意到
observers noticed galaxies
星系在形状和大小上有着多样性
came in a variety of shapes and sizes.
主要有两种 螺旋星系
The two main types of galaxy are spiral galaxy,
就像是银河 薄碟形有螺旋臂
Like our Milky Way, which have spiral arms in a thin disc.
椭圆的星系 象球形或椭圆形
And elliptical galaxies, which sort of more spherical or elliptically shape,
没有螺旋臂
they don't have spiral arms.
螺旋星系中有大量的气体和灰尘
The spiral galaxies have a lot of gas and dust in them
正在形成新的星体
for which new stars forming right now.
椭圆星系
Whereas the elliptical galaxies
象是星体形成好久了
seems to formed their stars long ago.
没有大量的气体和灰尘 新的星体不再形成
They don't have that much gas and dust so they are not forming stars right now.
还有不规则的星系
There are also irregular galaxies
通常他们有大量气体和灰尘但不是螺旋状的
which generally have a lot of gas and dust but not in a nice spiral form.
观察遥远处星辰的沉积物
Detecting these far off accumulations of stars
成了简单工作
is made easier when the astronomers
在天文学家研究灯塔爆破流时
search the streaming blasting beacons
在爆破流中心的附近找到许多沉积物
found near the center of many of them.
很多星系的中心都在激烈动荡中
Violent and erratic hearts beat at the center of many alien galaxies.
散发出很多能量
sending out so much energy
产生的能量胜过
they can overwhelm the amount of energy produced
其星系所有恒星产生能量的总和
by all of other stars within them.
它们有活跃的核心
These are the active galactic nuclei.
所以我们可以看到一些星系
So we can look at some galaxies
我们发现星系拥有强大的中心化的动力
and we find that they have at their very centers, very powerful engines
产生了大量的光
that are producing a tremendous amount of light.
我们知道它们是非常遥远的
We can tell they are far away.
即使这样 我们观察到的光也是很耀眼
and yet they are still very bright when you look them.
可见它们有很强的能量
so they must tremendously powerful
每秒都要爆发出大量的能量
dumping a lot of energy out every second.
活跃星系有剧烈和有力核心
Amount the most violent and powerful of the active galactic nuclei
这个神秘的现象叫 类星体
the mysterious phenomena called quasares.
当我们观察类星体时 类星体星状物
When we look at quasares, quasar stellar objects
看它们有多远 有些非常耀眼
and see how far away they are, some of them tremendously bright.
最亮的一个
The brightest one
比我们的太阳要耀眼一万亿倍
it about a trillion of times as bright as our sun.
惊人的电磁能量流
Spectacular streams of electromagnetic energy,
灯塔般照亮数百万英里的天空
right beacons lighting of the sky for billions miles.
这些高能源向我们展示了
These high energy sources provide a stunning reminder
宇宙的能量 照明
of the Universe's power to illuminate.
类星体自己可能比整个星系都亮
A quasar itself can be brighter than entire galaxy.
当我们观看类星体象C273的时候
So, when we look at a quasar like 3 C 273
用哈勃天文望远镜拍摄的景象
the Hubble space telescope took some images of this
我们发现它喷发出大量的物质
and we found it has big jet of material shooting out beside it.
几乎与星系相仿
almost the size of the galaxy itself.
活跃星系核 真是奇怪
These is really weird things, these active galactic nucleus.
活跃星系核显示
As active galactic nucleus show,
太空是剧烈变化的地方
space is a violent place.
还有将要发生的大碰撞
And as it turns out there is a massive collision going on,
就在我们自己院儿里
right in our own backyard.
罪魁祸首
The culprit,
大犬座矮星系
a galaxy called the Canis major dwarf galaxy.
就名字而言 矮星系就是小星系
As the name implies dwarfed galaxies are small.
所以很难被发现
making them even more difficult to detect.
现在大犬座矮星系正朝着银河运动
Now, the Canis major dwarf galaxy is taking aim at the Milky Way.
两星系发生冲突是引力的原因
Two galaxies on a collision course from which, thanks to the gravity,
无法逃避
there is no escape.
当小的星系接近大星系时
When a small galaxy comes too close a large galaxy
潮汐作用可使其被拉伸和扭曲
the tidal effects can cause it to be stretched out and distorted.
所以大星系的引力
So the gravitational attraction of the larger galaxy
将会推压小星系内的星体
will actually pull and stretch the stars in the smaller galaxy.
这一系列的星系
So a collection of galaxies
它们的位置和大小
that has relative spacing compare its size,
就象冰上的冰球似的
about like the way pucks are laid out on the ice,
所有这些星系将彼此平等地穿越太空
all these galaxies would be moving through space with respect to one another.
每隔一段时间 就会有星系碰撞到另一个
Every once in a while, one of these galaxies is going to bonk into another one.
当碰撞时 星系的形状会扭曲和延伸
When that happens, the shape of galaxy will actually become distorted and stretched out.
冰球是固体 但星系由众星组成
These pucks are solid, but galaxies are made individual stars.
它被扭曲并撕裂成潮汐尾
Each of which feels the of gravity of all the others, And it becomes distorted and torn into tidal tails,
在不同的方向形成巨大的星弧
A big swooping arc of stars in neither directions.
远处星系的星群
And that's how the once far off stars from an alien galaxy
快速穿越数亿英里
blazing through space for millions upon billions of miles
并入我们星系的情况
can end up blending right in our own.
但是群星是加何形成星系的？
But what caused these stars to come together in galaxies?
为什么宇宙中物质会融合到一起
Why has matter and mass of the universe fused
形成如此壮观的结构？
into these spectacular structures?
为了寻找答案 我们需要将时钟倒拨
To find the answer we have to turn our clocks back
数百万 数十亿年以前
millions and billions of years ago.
回到足够远的以前 你会发现一个点
Go back far enough and you reach a point
所有的物质
where all the matter
时间和空间都被压缩
and the space and the time become compressed
成一个无限小的点
and compacted into an infinitely small point.
重力奇异的无限维度
A gravitational singularity of infinite dimension.
这个点在大爆炸时壮观地爆炸了
It is point that exploded with spectacular Big Bang.
长时间以前
A long time ago, the matter and energy
构成每个星系的物质和能量
that would make up every alien galaxy
相距并不远
wasn't far away.
组成星系的所有东西
Everything that ever became an alien galaxy
都在这个重力奇异的点里
sprung forth from a gravitational singularity
然后发生了大爆炸
that has come to be known as the Big Bang.
假如在你脑海里反转宇宙的发展
If you run a film of the universe backwards in your mind
最后你会发现一个密度极高点
eventually you get to a point where the density would become extremely high.
回到足够远的以前
If you go far enough
宇宙中所有的物质和能量都在一起
all the mass and energy that we have at Universe would be in a single location
你会发现无限地密集
you will find infinite density.
我们认为宇宙的膨胀给我们很深的启示
We think that the expansion of the Universe is telling us something very profound.
这个时间是宇宙的起点
That the Universe has a beginning point in the time.
在那个时刻 大爆炸之后
In those moment, after the Big Bang
宇宙的定律和恒星成型
the rules of our Universe and stars took shape.
所有的定律中万有引力最主要
And one of the biggest rules was the law of gravity.
大爆炸之后  宇宙在膨胀
After the Big Bang, the universe of course was expanding
但有的部分比其他部分密度大
but there were some parts that were denser than others.
密度大的部分引力吸引
Those denser parts started gravitationally contracting
它们形成了星系
and they formed galaxies.
气块吸引了星云逐渐形成了恒星
Pockets of gas within those gravitational contracting clouds formed stars
因为气块的引力比
because those pockets gravitationally contracted
一般的星云的引力大
even more than the general cloud of gas.
可能要上亿年
It's would take hundreds of millions years
第一个星系才形成
for the first galaxy to coalesce into existing.
我们不知它们形成的精确时间
We don't know exactly when this happened
但我们可在大爆炸之后10亿年看到几乎所有的星系
But we can see pretty much all galaxies about a billion years after the Big Bang.
我能看到的最早的东西
And the earliest objects that I can see
是大爆炸之后五亿年的
is about 500 million years after Big Bang.
所以就在这个期间
So it's within this period
我们认为早期的物质转化成了星系
we think the very early objects switched on.
我们还不知道第一个星系形成的时间
We haven't yet found a time when there were no galaxies at all.
对其他星系的进一步研究
To learn more about alien galaxies
需要解开银河系
we need to solve many mysteries of our Milky Way's
我们自己的星系之谜
own place in the universe.
当我们想了解银河系的结构时
When we want to look at the structure of our galaxy
面临的困难是我们身在其中
the difficulty we run into is that we are inside of it.
我们只能看到从内部看到的景象
We can only see what we can see from inside.
灰尘和气体遮挡我们的视线
More over there is dust and gas blocking our lines of sight
就我们在银河系的位置 看不了多远
and we can't see very far, from our position in our galaxy
无论那个方向都是一样
in many different directions.
银河系是一棒旋星系
We think the Milky Way is a barred spiral galaxy
10万光年方圆
reaching about 100 thousand light years across
核厚3000光年
with a 3000 light year thick core.
宇宙中的大部分星系较小
Most galaxies in Universe are smaller.
银河系和很多遥其它星系一样就像是城市
The Milky Way, and many alien galaxies, are like cities
中心密度大 周边密度小
with a central dense core and less dense suburbs.
对于螺旋星系 象我们的银河系
For spiral galaxies, like our own Milky Way
从中心到周边的旅程
that means a trip to visit the suburbs
可没有象城市的高速公路
is not unlike a trip on the freeways.
我们星系中所有的星都围绕着中心旋转
All the stars in our galaxy are orbiting around the center.
我们距离中心大约三万光年
We are about 30 thousand light years away from the center
我们要用2.5亿年
and it takes us about 250 million years
才能完成这漫长的一圈
to make one orbit around the galaxy.
群星都在自己的轨道上绕着星系转
Now the stars are all in their orbits, all moving around the galaxy
那么我们看到的螺旋是如何形成的呢？
so, what causes the beautiful spirals arms that we see?
看 这儿有一种密度波
Well, there's a sort of density wave
在星系的这个区域 星的密度大
and area where the stars and galaxy are just a little bit denser
比星系其他地方的星的数目多
more packed together than the rest of the galaxy.
有的星进入密度波 有的星离开密度波
Different stars move in the density wave, different stars move out.
但密度波还在那儿 就是旋转臂
But the density waves stays there and that's the spiral arm.
就象高速公路上堵车一样
So like the same way a traffic jam get starts on the freeway.
当不知什么原因一个星慢下来的时候
Something happens makes maybe one star slow down
由于万有引力相互作用
some sort of gravitational interaction
其它的星群也要慢下来
and other stars slow down in response to it.
就这么着突然 你遇上堵车了
And all of a sudden, you got traffic jam.
所以 星系的自然形态
So, galaxies seem to naturally form
就是那些螺旋的密度波
these spiral dense waves.
250万光年之外
Two and half million light year away,
我们的对手在那里
a menacing counterpart to our galaxy sits and swirls
密切注意着银河系
casting a wary eye towards the Milky Way.
那是我们星系的舞伴
It's a dance partner of our galaxy
最大的邻居 最大的冤家
our biggest neighbor and our biggest nemesis.
它是M31  也叫仙女座星系
It's called M31, better known as the Andromeda galaxy.
仙女座星系和我们的银河系大小相仿
The Andromeda galaxy is about the same size as our Milky Way
方圆十万光年
it's about 100 thousand light year across.
是螺旋星系
It's a spiral galaxy,
可能正在形成的活跃恒星
it had perhaps a little bit less active stars formation going on right now
比银河系少点儿 其它非常相似
than our Milky Way, but otherwise it's quite similar.
仙女座可能也是由数个
Andromeda is probably also the product of several
小星系合并或交互形成
smaller galaxies that coalesced or interacted overtime.
其中一个星系
One of those galaxies may be responsible
带给仙女座两个核心
for Andromeda's double nucleus
在它的中心可看到两大星团
Two huge clumps stars find at its center
在地球上 我们注视
On Earth, we've been keeping an eye
我们的繁星众多的邻居数个世纪了
on our trillion stars neighbor for centuries.
10世纪的波斯文记载着
Persian texts of the 10th century mention
天空中小小的星云
the small cloud in the skies,
只是当时
but at the time
无法知道仙女座是完全独立的星系
there was no way knowing that Andromeda was an entirely separate galaxy
有250万光年之遥
two and half million light years away.
这是宇宙中最遥远的天体
That makes it the furthest object in the universe
可直接被肉眼观测到
you can see with the naked eye.
尽管银河系有能力吸收
Well the Milky Way may be able to absorb
大犬座矮星系的碰撞
the impact of a colliding dwarf galaxy,
可和仙女座星系的碰撞不仅不可避免
A clash with the Andromeda galaxy is not only inevitable,
还要给我们的星系造成永久的变迁
but will forever change the local galactic landscape.
引力 宇宙中最常用的能量
Gravity, the Universe's most prolific power
这个吸引力使仙女座和
is the force that's pulling Andromeda and
银河系慢慢接近
the Milky Way closer and closer.
会有一天 在远远的未来
And someday, in the far off future,
这两个螺旋巨头会碰撞
these two spiral titans will collide.
你要是观察银河系和仙女座星系
If you look at the Milky Way galaxy  and the Andromeda galaxy
离我们最近的大星系的话
the nearest large galaxy to us
就会发现 它们以惊人的速度在接近中
they are actually approaching each other at a fairly astounding rate
每秒有数百公里
to several hundred Kilometers every second.
现在它们离的挺远 几亿年后的一天
They are very far apart right now, but in the next few billion years, sometime,
它们将会相互攻击对方
they will be right up against each other.
在某种意义上说碰撞即将发生
And so collision in a sense, imminent.
可能恒星不会物理地碰撞
Probably no stars will physically hit each other.
恒星之间空间很大
there's just so much space between the stars.
但仙女座和我们的碰撞
But when Andromeda collides with us,
会对银河系造成巨大的影响
It'll have a huge impact on the Milky Way.
会有东西被吸入中心的黑洞里
Some things will get throw into black hole in the middle
也会有恒星被抛入太空
some stars will get ripped off and throw the way into space.
整个夜空会发生戏剧性的变化
So it will be dramatic, and the entire night sky will change.
其它星系的运动情况
The constant motion of alien galaxies
和时间框架的参与
and the time frames involved
可能很难进行比较
may be hard to compared.
仙女座离银河系足够近
Andromeda is close enough to the Milky Way
它们之间的引力
that their gravitational attraction
拉近了之间的距离
brings them closer together.
另一方面 我们看到的几乎所有的星系
But elsewhere, almost all the alien galaxies we see
都在离我们远去
are moving away from us.
以常识来看 象炸弹爆炸
In our common experience like a exploding bomb
所有的东西都从中心炸走
everything explode away from a center.
但是在我们宇宙有这样的空旷的中心吗？
Now, is there an empty center to our Universe?
我们在星系的外壳上远离
Are we on a shell of galaxies flying away
发生原始爆炸的地方吗？
from whatever the original explosion was?
不 真的太奇怪了
No. And that is the amazing thing.
我们的宇宙中空间自己在膨胀
In our Universe space itself is expanding.
每一小片空间都是
every little bit of space.
我手之间的空间都有膨胀的压力
the space right here between my hands has a pressure to expand.
最早观测到膨胀的是天文学家哈勃
It's this expansion first detected by astronomer Edwin Hubble
由此为基础建立了现代天文学
that laid the foundation for much of modern astronomy.
所以说宇宙随着时间而膨胀
So the Universe expands with time
空间自己也在膨胀
and space itself actually expanding.
我们举一个一唯的例子说明宇宙
If you take a one-dimensional example of a Universe,
这是个假想的宇宙
Here, here is hypothetical Universe
我用在皮管上的乒乓球代表星系
I got this ping pong balls, which are the galaxies
我能将皮管拉开
on this rubber hose. I can expand that hose,
所有的星系都相互远离
and all the galaxies move away from the others.
看到了吗？实际上 如果我们说这儿这个
See that? And in fact, if we focus our attention on this one here
离的远的那个远离的
the ones that are farther away from that
要比离的近的这个快一点儿
move faster than the ones that are closer in.
因为这个和那个远的与
Because there is more space, there is more tube
这个和那个近的比
between this one here and the distant one
空间大 皮管的距离远
than this one and the nearby one.
某种意义上讲 这是个很好的模型
So that's, in a sense, a good model
来说明哈勃的观测结果
for Hubble's observation
在指定的时间内 远的星系
that at a given time, the more distant galaxies
比近的星系移动的要快
move faster than the nearby galaxies.
还要注意 没有那个星系
Notice also that no galaxy can claim
可以说它就是宇宙的中心
that is the unique center of the Universe.
当然啦
Sure!
对于这个来说所有其他的都远离了
For this one prospective all others are moving away.
假如你要在这个
But if I were put myself on this one here,
也可以说所有其他的星系都远离了
I would say that all the galaxies are moving away from this one as well.
不管你在哪个星系
So no matter which galaxy you're on,
都会看到其它星系在离开
we see the others moving away from you.
这就是所谓宇宙的均匀膨胀
That's what happens in a uniformly expanding Universe
没有特殊的星系可以成为宇宙的中心
There is no galaxy that can say that it is the unique center of the Universe.
在早期人们认为地球是一切的中心
If you think back to earlier times, it was thought that the Earth was the center of everything.
地球是宇宙的中心 行星和太阳
It was the center of the Universe, and the planets and the sun
都围绕着地球
all orbited around the Earth.
群星每天都环绕着地球
And the stars everyday made one trip around the Earth.
接着我们发现太阳是许多恒星中的一员
Then we discovered that our Sun was one of many stars
据我们所知
and our sun was cruising around through the Universe
我们的太阳在宇宙中巡航
as we knew it.
但哈勃的发现
But this discovery by Hubble
告诉我们 不只我们的行星是众多行星中的一员
told us that not only was our planet one of many planets
我们的恒星太阳是众多恒星中的一员
and our star, the sun, was one of many stars
而且我们的星系和行星 太阳一样
but that our galaxy was one of many galaxies
也是众多星系中的一员
presumable like many others.
我们的世界观和在宇宙的位置变了
It really changed our world view and our place in the Universe
我们的星系不过是普通的一个星系
to think that our galaxy is an ordinary galaxy.
让我们看看谁是我们的星系邻居？
So just what's in our galactic neighbourhood?
认识一下我们的紧邻
Meet the local group of galaxies.
一群还在增加的成员
A group with ever increasing membership.
我们附近的星系群是个小群
Our local group of galaxies is a small group
这群大约有三打星系
or a cluster of about 3 dozen galaxies.
我们银河系和仙女座星系 M31
Our Milky Way and the Andromeda galaxy, M31
是两个绩优星系
are the two dominant galaxies.
星系群中其它的星系
most of the galaxies in our local group
都是矮星星系
are small dwarf galaxies.
这些星系都有几个小的卫星星系
These galaxies each have collections of small satellite galaxies
象奴隶一样围绕着它们
that are in their thrall. that orbit around them.
大的星系之间都受到对方的引力影响
And these big galaxies all feel the influence of each other's masses
相互绕行 所有的星系
and orbit around each other. So all of these galaxies,
小的绕着大的转
the small galaxies are orbiting the big galaxies,
大的相互绕着转
and big galaxies are also orbiting echo other.
这个有三十多个星系的星系群
That's a group of about 30 or more galaxies
围绕着它们共同的质量中心旋转
that all orbit around a common center mass.
在我们星系群的两个著名的矮星星系
The most well known dwarf members of the local group,
是大 小麦哲伦星云
two galaxies known as Large and Small Magellanic clouds.
科学家现在认为 受银河系引力影响
Scientists now think the clouds orbit the Milky Way
它们在围绕着银河系旋转
thanks to the tidal influence of our galaxy.
引力是双刃剑
Gravity of course is a two way street.
可以认为来自星云的引力
It's believe the gravitational pull from these clouds
同样扭曲了我们星系的部分圆盘
has also distorted parts of our own galactic disc.
由恒星释放出的能量测定
By measuring the energy it emits from the stars
大 小麦哲伦星云
in the Small and Large Magellanic clouds,
天文学家认为 它们的组成
astronomers believe they are made of
和我们的星系不同
different stuff than our galaxy.
相对银河系 星云中富含氢和氦
The clouds are richer in hydrogen and helium than the Milky Way
金属含量少
and with fewer metals.
科学家认为这表明
Scientists think this means
星云中的恒星是新星
the stars are younger in the clouds.
星云和银河系之间的引力舞蹈
The gravitational dance between the clouds and Milky Way
看起来进行了数亿年了
has likely be going on for billion years.
同时一种不同的和更加神秘的战斗
But all the while, a different and much more mysterious battle
发生在银河系的中心
is going on back in the center of  Milky Way.
当你到了银河系的中心
Because when you head for the center of our galaxy
穿过了宇宙灰尘 气体和星辰
once you get through all the dust, gas and all the older stars,
你会发现大吃一惊的东西
you find something so insanely frighting
时间和空间的正常规则在这儿是不适用的
the normal rules of time and space do not apply.
在银河的中心或许在每个星系的中心
For lurking at the heart of Milky Way and perhaps every alien galaxies
是一个有贪婪的胃口的超级怪兽
is a massive beast with a ravenous appetite.
一个无法逃脱的怪兽
A beast from which there is no escape.
在我们的星系--银河系的核心区域
There is a region at the core of our galaxy, the Milky Way
那里什么都无法逃脱
where nothing escapes.
这里有去无回
This is the point of no return
一个巨大的超级黑洞
a super massive black hole.
黑洞是一种天体物理学物体
A black hole is an astrophysical object,
有巨大的质量 微小的体积
that has so much mass, in such a small volume
它的引力非常强大
that the gravitational force is so strong
就连光也没有足够的能量逃脱
that even light doesn't have enough energy to escape.
黑洞形成于
Black holes can form
或者巨大的恒星生命终止时的爆炸
either when massive stars explode at the end of its life
其核心崩溃成为黑洞
and the core of the star collapses into a black hole,
或者在星系的中心形成黑洞
or you can have super massive black holes at the centers of the galaxies.
多么大？
How massive?
设想一下接近400万倍的太阳的质量
Try nearly 4 million times the mass of our Sun.
有时候黑洞吞噬整个恒星
Sometimes black holes swallow entire stars
引发剧烈爆炸产生伽玛射线暴
creating fierce explosions called gamma ray bursts.
要产生伽玛射线暴
In order to emit a gamma ray,
物体的温度要达到几十亿度
an object has to be billions of degree in temperature
或者万亿度 不可置信地热
or even trillions, so we're seeing something incredibly hot.
有时候一百亿光年外的星系
In some cases the galaxies were as much as 10 billion light years away
产生伽玛射线暴时亮到
and the gamma ray bursts had been so bright
用副望远镜
that if you had a pair of binoculars
在正确的时间和正确的角度
and you were actually looking at right part of the sky at the right time
就可以看到伽玛射线暴的余晖
you would have been able to see visible afterglow of the gamma rays.
就用望远镜
That's using binoculars
看到宇宙那边的景物
to see something that's on the other side of the Universe
一百亿光年外呀
10 billion light years away.
你能想象到那是什么样的爆炸吗？
Can you imagine what sort of explosion that was?
假如我们的星系中心有个巨大的超级黑洞
So if there is a super massive black hole at the center of our galaxy
相同的黑洞
are similar black hole
在每个星系中心都有吗？
located at center of all alien galaxies?
当观察相邻星系的时
When we look at neighboring galaxies
最近的结果
and this is a recent result
我们看到大部分星系
we find that most galaxies
其中心有个巨大的超级黑洞
seem to have very massive black holes in the center
范围是数百万甚至数亿倍
that range from millions even billion times
我们的太阳的质量
as much as our Sun.
这对星系来说似乎很常见和普通
It appears to be a very common and ordinary aspect of a galaxy.
黑洞吞噬物质
Black holes swallow matter
但宇宙1%的一少半
but less than one half of 1 % of our Universe
相信是可以观察到的物质
it's believed to be made up of observable matter
象恒星 行星 气体和星尘
such as the stars, planets, gas and dust.
大爆炸后形成的物质如何运作？
So what accounts for the rest stuff created in aftermath of the Big Bang?
到底是什么形成了星系？
What really fills up alien galaxies?
科学家的最佳推测
A scientist's best guess
是种神秘物质--暗物质
is a mysterious substance call dark matter.
暗物质是神奇的东西
Dark matter is fantastic stuff.
我们知道它存在 我们知道它在吸引物质
We know that it exists, we know that it gravitationally pulls on things.
暗黑物质存在的最佳证据之一
One of the best pieces of evidences for the existence of dark matter
是螺旋星系的自转
is that spiral galaxies are spinning
比它们应有的速度快
more quickly than they would be spinning
除非有看不到的物质
unless there were extra unseeing material
导致它们的自转加速
causing them to spin that fast.
加州理工的埃利斯教授用一项新技术创新地
Caltech professor Richard Ellis has pioneered a new technique
建立了宇宙的三唯地图
to create a three-dimensional map of the Universe
包括暗物质
including the dark matter.
这是首次由动态数据给出的暗示
This is the first hint from dynamical data
宇宙中存在大量的暗物质
that there's a lot of dark matter in the Universe.
我们也可通过非凡的现象发现暗物质
We can also detect dark matter by really remarkable phenomenon
就是由爱因斯坦预测 现在被天文学应用的
which is predicted by Einstein and is now in great in astronomy
引力透镜效应
which we call gravitational lensing.
暗物质使通过它的光线弯曲
Dark matter bends light passing through it
很象块不平的玻璃
much like a curved piece of glass
光波被物质弯曲
The light rays are bent by material
在哪里看到这种弯曲的光线
and where we can see the signature of this bending of the light rays
就是说那里就有大量暗物质的存在
we can infer that there's lot of dark matter present.
我们无法直接看到暗物质
We don't have to see the dark matter directly
它既不发光也不反光
it doesn't shine, it doesn't scatter light
但我们可以推测它的存在 通过
but we can infer its presence from the effect it has
穿过暗物质的光线
on light rays that are coming
所受到的它的影响
through the clump of dark matter.
所以我们知道暗物质的存在
So, we know the dark matter is there
我们能画它的分布图
we can make maps of how it is distributed
尽管我们无法直接看到
even if we cannot see it directly.
引力透镜效应更大的优势
So one farther advantage of gravitational lensing
是它像放大镜一样
it is it just like a magnifying glass.
通过它观察的时 想对于没有它
So when you look through it, things are bigger and brighter
物体会大点儿 亮点儿
than they would be if you didn't have it.
你可以认为它是太空中天然的望远镜
So if you think about it, it's like a natural telescope in space.
尽管暗物质的作用
While dark matter plays a central role
在星系的诞生和进化很重要
in the birth and evolving life of the galaxies
还有一种暗力量起了部分作用
there is another dark force partially responsible for its growth.
以宇宙角度来看 星系在快速远离我们而去
On a cosmic scale, the galaxies are rushing away from us
因为宇宙在不停的膨胀
due to the continuing expansion of the Universe.
如果宇宙在膨胀 什么力量推动它的澎胀？
So, if the Universe is expanding, what's driving it?
现在科学家只有一种答案
The only answer scientists can come up with for now
一种神秘的暗能量
a mysterious dark energy.
暗能量某种角度上比暗物质还要怪
Dark energy is even stranger in some ways than dark matter.
暗能量
Dark energy
导致了宇宙膨胀一直到现在
is causing the Universe to expand right now
随时间越来越快
faster and faster with time.
这个宇宙概念的膨胀运动
This expansion set in motion at the Universe's conception
已被加速了数十亿年了
has accelerated in the last few billion years
因为暗能量 发起的运动随时间增长而增长
because the dark energy that creates the movement has increased over time.
自然地 维系星系们联系的引力
By nature, the gravitational force they binds galaxies together
随着它们之间的距离增加逐渐减弱
decrease over time as the space between them increases.
不是增加引力
So, instead of having a gravitational pull
不是减缓宇宙的膨胀
instead of slowing down the expansion of the Universe
暗能量在加速宇宙的膨胀
dark energy is speeding up the expansion of the Universe
并且已经加速了四 五十亿年了
and it has been doing that for the passing 4 or 5 billion of years.
经过或许数十亿 数万亿年
In perhaps a billion, trillion more years
宇宙的命运和对它的影响 黑洞
the fate of the Universe and the impact, the black holes
暗物质
dark matter
和暗能量终会被人类
and dark energy have on the mankind
所了解
will finally be known.
当一颗恒星离黑洞太近时
When a star get too close to a black hole
星系的中心将会出现混乱
at the heart of an alien galaxy, chaos arises.
那是又一个探索
That's one of the findings for
星系进化的任务
the galaxies evolution explorer mission
简称 加里克 (星系演化探测器).
or GALEX (GALaxies Evolution eXplorer).
加里克是一架紫外线望远镜
The Galaxy Evolution Explorer is an ultraviolet telescope
用来观测宇宙的紫外线波长
that observes the Universe in ultraviolet wavelengths.
那些波长非常敏感于
And at these wavelengths you are very sensitive
新星的研究
to studying young stars,
敏感于星系中恒星的形成
stars formation in the galaxies
回到宇宙年龄一半的时候
back to half the age of universe.
数十亿年以前
billions of years ago.
当然也要观测那些发光火焰的紫外线
However, we also look in ultraviolet for these luminous flames
发出于被黑洞吞噬的恒星
from when a star is swallowed by a black hole.
当恒星再也坚持不住时
The star can't hold itself together anymore
它被肢解了
and it is ripped apart,
从恒星来的气体陷入了黑洞
and the gas from the star plunges into the black hole.
一些气体会被高速甩出
Some of the gas would be ejected from the system at high velocities
但大部份气体会陷入了黑洞
but some fraction of the gas will plunge into the black hole
这个过程将被加热到极高温度
and in that process will heat up to very high temperatures
散发出发光火焰的紫外线和X射线
and give off a luminous flame of ultraviolet and X-ray radiation.
感谢加里克  苏维·吉扎里和其他的研究者
Thanks to the GALEX, Suvi Gezari and other researches
可以看到
were able to watch all happened
四十亿光年之外发生的事情
4 billion light years away.
加里克--哈勃和史匹哲不久会有个新邻居
Galex, Hubble and the Spitzer space telescope will soon be get a new neighbor
用来拍摄星系的图片
designed to help catch images of alien galaxies.
韦伯太空望远镜定于2013年发射
The James Webb space telescope is due to launch in 2013
用于探索红外光谱
designed to explore the infrared spectrum
开一先河
like never before.
使用韦伯望远镜
Using the Webb telescope
科学家希望可以穿过恒星和星尘的遮挡
scientists hope to be able to see through dust and the stars
看到银河系的中心
that block our view of the Milky Way center.
获得更为清晰的图片
and provide more complete picture
不只是我们的星系
not just our galaxy
而且所有的星系
but of all alien galaxies.
韦伯太空望远镜
The James Webb space telescope
和哈勃望远镜有两方面不同
differs from the Hubble space telescope in two aspects.
第一 更强大 其有一个更大的反射镜
Firstly, it's more powerful, it has a greater mirror.
其次 它可以工作于略长的
Secondly, it is actually working at slightly longer
红外线波长
infrared waves lengths.
哈勃和韦伯它们共同的地方
What Hubble and Webb have in common
是脱离了流动大气的影响
is the power to see beyond atmospheric turbulence
流动大气使天文学家得不到
that prevent astronomers to get picture perfect images
99 % 的天空的完美图片
from 99 % of the sky.
地球大气是动荡的
The Earth atmosphere is turbulent.
它影响了恒星发出的光
It blows out the images from stars.
如果地球没有大气 我们看到的恒星
So if the Earth had no atmosphere we would see stars basically
会是完美的光点
really perfect dots of light.
但是光在通过大气的时候
But what happens is that because light passes through the atmosphere
发生弯曲 变成分散的光斑
it's distorted, it turns into a fuzz blob.
有两个办法解决这个问题
It turns out there are two ways to fix this.
一个是到太空去
One way is to go the space
另一个不是处理地上的望远镜
the other way is to instead fix the telescope on the ground
而是消除大气带来的影响
so that it removes the effect of the turbulence
这项技术就是自适应光学测量法
and that is a technology know as Adaptive optics.
自适应光学测量星系影像的方法
The Adaptive optics measures the image of a galaxy
是消除光线对其他发光体的反射
by the way its light reflects off another lighting object
比如附近的明亮的恒星
like nearby bright star.
自适应光学需要很亮的恒星作参照
To do Adaptive optics sensing you need a very bright star
当然在大气中测量时
because of course, you are making measurements of the atmosphere
每秒要达到数百次甚至上千次
hundreds or thousands of times per second.
需要很亮的东西作参照
so you need something bright look it.
大部分恒星都不够亮
Most stars are not bright enough to do this.
所以在柯奇工作的夏威夷天文台
At observatories like the Keck in Hawaii
自适应光学系统要使用激光束
the Adaptive optics uses a laser beam
提供拍摄时的光的需求
to help create the light needed for the snap shoots.
可以用它指到天空中任何一点
You can point anywhere you want on the sky
不只是1%的天空 你可看到绝大部分天空
so instead of looking at only 1% of the sky, you can look at most of the sky
得到非常高的分辫率的清晰图像
with a very very high resolution, very sharp images.
用这个方法 能提升图片10到20倍的清晰度
In this way you can make images 10-20 times sharper from the ground
参照于不使用自适应光学
than you could without adaptive optics.
这是我们设计的另一个工具
It's just another tool in the kit of course designed
为将奇异的其它星系的图片
to bring the fantastic reaches of alien galaxies
带回地球
back down to Earth.
宇宙 当然
The Universe, of course
万物之家 比我们的地球大
is home to many things larger than our small planet Earth
比我们的太阳系大
larger than our Solar System
比我们银河系大
larger than our galaxy.
想想我们的银河
To think that our Milky Way
只是可探测的宇宙中
is just one of hundreds billions galaxies
上千亿个星系之一
in the observable Universe
可以这样想 我们是比地球大好多的
it's really feels like you are part of something much larger
东西的一部分
than our small planet Earth.
无论你是否喜欢 这就是我们在宇宙的地位
Like or not this is our place in the Universe.
一点一点地累积
A speck on a speck on a speck.
小小的蓝色地球 生命绿洲
Just one tiny blue green oasis of life,
遨游在浩瀚的星系海洋中
swimming in a vast ocean of alien galaxies.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing